Guide to the Records of the Institute for Computing in the Humanities RG.37.24
New York University Archives
Records of the Institute for Computer Research in the Humanities
1964-1982
1964-1969
New York University Archives
New York University. Institute for Computer Research in the Humanities
RG.37.24
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
The Institute for Computer Research in the Humanities was formed at New York University's University College in 1965, when a need developed for a method of organizing research and criticism in the humanities. Founders of the Institute aimed to eliminate an unproductive boundary between the humanities and technology in an attempt to advance scholarly research.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open to researchers.
Arrangement Note
The folders in this collection are arranged alphabetically.
Provenance
This collection was created by Anna Pollin, Director of the New York University program in Spain and founder of the Institute for Computer Research in the Humanities. She transferred the collection to Professor Bayrd Still of the New York University Department of History in 1982. The documents were later transferred to the New York University Archives.
History
The Institute for Computer Research in the Humanities began after Dr. Alice Pollin of the Spanish Department at University College proposed a project that involved creating a computer index of the Revista de Filogia Espanola, a collection of Hispanic literature and linguistics. This project illuminated the potential for merging computer technology with humanities research to advance research and writing techniques. Early proposals for the program included projects that would catalogue literature and literary criticism and develop technology for music analysis. The Institute was officially created in September 1965. It actively promoted computer research in the humanities for over five years. In July 1969 the Institute was shuttered due to lack of funding.
Scope and Contents Note
The collection comprises paper documentation relating to the Institute for Computer Research in the Humanities. Materials concerning the founding of the Institute include correspondence, a record of its first meeting, and proposals for the Institute and its constituent projects within the disciplines of Spanish literature, classics, and musicology. Organizational activities are reflected in conference materials, newsletters, and press clippings.
- Series I: History, 1964-1982; 1964-1969
  - Conference Material, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - News Clippings, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - News Letters, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Proposal: The Genesis of an Idea, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Proposal, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Proposal, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Record of First Meeting, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Revista De Filogia Espanola, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)